that we refuse to remain paralyzed before our sins, and instead take the faltering steps
that we can today to open ourselves to the holy strength that has overcome even death
itself. Instead of obsessing about how well we are doing, we must mindfully entrust ourselves
to the mercy of the one who is healing and strengthening us in ways that we cannot know
as we reorient our lives to him, even in small and
imperfect ways. We must also take the heart, the Lord's words to the man after his healing.
He said, See you are well, sin no more, that nothing worse befalls you. Obeying that command
requires remaining vigilant, as we mindfully turn away from the familiar passions and subtle
temptations that so easily ensnare us. Entering into the holy joy of Paska is truly an eternal
of sharing ever more fully in the healing
of Christ as we become more like Him in holiness. And the only way to do that is to rise, take up our
beds and walk each day of our lives in obedience to Him as best we can. That is His command to us all,
and it's the only way to know the great joy of His victory over sin and death. For Christ is
risen, indeed He is risen, in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the Holy Spirit, one God,
Amen.
You have been listening to Eastern Christian Insights with Father Philip LaMasters,
homilies from St. Luke Orthodox Church in Abilene, Texas.
This has been a listener-supported presentation of Ancient Faith Radio.
Glory to Jesus Christ, glory forever,
you're listening to ancientfaithradio.com.
He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall,
And he will be the
light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him,
enable praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits,
angels, demons and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat,
secular materialism to see and to
no reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen De Young, host this live Colin show,
focused on enchantment in creation,
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, giant killers and dragon slayers.
You are listening to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
My co-host, Father Stephen D'Young,
is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana,
Keijin Country, and I am Father and your Stephen Damick
in Emmaus, Pennsylvania, exiled among Yankees.
And if you're listening to a slide,
you can call in at 855 AF radio.
Again, that's 855-237-2346.
As you just heard the voice of Steve Say,
Matushka Trudy is taking calls tonight,
which we are gonna get to in the second part
the show.
But first, a word from our sponsors.
Lord of Spirits is brought to you by our listeners with help from the Theoria School of Filmmaking.
Theoria School of Filmmaking is the first Orthodox film school.
The primary instructor is Jonathan Jackson, a faithful Orthodox Christian speaker writer
and five time Emmy Ward winner.
To learn more about Theoria, please visit TheoriaFilm.org.
That's TH-E-O-R-I-A-Film.org.
You know.
I feel like we could do more with our sponsors, right?
Yeah.
They support the show.
You know, you read the thing.
Yeah.
There needs to be something here to more actively involve
our listeners, right?
Like a decoder wheel of some sort or one of those rings
with the whistle in it.
Oh, yeah.
Or like, maybe they could download and print a coupon
for a free bag of Flamin' Hot Cheetos, right?
Like, some kind of way.
Give away.
to get them invested in our sponsors.
Right.
Yeah.
Or I can add out as a challenge.
I don't know who.
It's out there.
I could start dropping encoded references
within the course of the ad.
And then they have to add them up over decipher them.
Right.
And then the Cheetos.
Yeah.
Because we're symbologists, right?
No.
Now it's different podcast.
So, all right.
We probably do it better.
Oh.
Probably true. Tonight we continue with our series on the fall of man and the second part is on the coming of sin into the world and its attack on mankind beginning with the person of keen the first son of Adam and Eve.
Now last time we talked about death and this time it's about sin.
But Father Stephen shouldn't sin really be associated with with Adam though isn't isn't that what the Bible says?
No.
All right, but also kind of yes. Yes.
Isn't that a meme?
Is that the meme of the pirate?
I think it's the opposite.
Yeah. Yes, but actually no, nobody actually is.
I don't know.
I don't think we made this explicit last time, but maybe we should.
And, you know, way back in the long ago time, in the before time,
for the grups, all died of the plague.
Uh...
We had the five-ish falls of the angels, and now we're in the midst of this series on
sort of the Three Falls of Man.
And when we talk about these Three Falls of Man, you know, most of not all of our listener
base unless you know it's from our material I imagine. Most of them are used to
just thinking of
the fall.
The fall.
Right.
As one thing.
And see the easy thing here to do here is to knock St. Augustine.
But I'm not going to knock St. Augustine.
I've come here to praise St. Augustine not to bury him.
Pain.
The first Shakespeare reference.
We don't do Shakespeare references very often.
That's good.
And so these three things that we're talking about of these episodes.
Bye.
last two weeks ago, the last episode we talked about the expulsion from Paradise.
Now, we're going to be talking about specifically Canes, about Canes line, leading up to the flood.
And then next time we're going to be talking about events surrounding the Tower of Babel.
All three of these you find discussed in Second Temple Jewish sources and in the Church Fathers.
and different church fathers, we'll just talk about church fathers.
different church fathers tend to stress one of the three, or they see one of the three is sort of being the pivotal one.
Yeah, while not denying the others. Right. Right. So senior anase of leone when we read on the apostolic preaching.
For him, the pivotal moment has to do with Genesis 6, 1 through 4 with stuff we're going to be talking about tonight and with the giants. Right.
corruption and sin that has to be destroyed by the flood. This is sort of
of the fall. Obviously he believes the expulsion from paradise happened. Right? Obviously he
talks about the Tower of Babel also, but for St. Irenaeus, sort of that, right? This from
Genesis 4 through 9, this is the sort of main event, right? If you read, you see,
the Sessary is demonstration of the gospel, he sees the tower of Bable as the main event.
He doesn't deny the expulsion for paradise happened.
He doesn't deny any of the events surrounding the flood.
But for him, it's the Tower of Bable
when the nations are divided
and the powers of principalities.
That for him is the sort of main central event.
And so part of how you could tell
it's the main central event is that when they come around
then to talk about Christ in the Gospel,
they're mainly talking about Christ
in terms of repairing that one.
Again, he also takes care of the others,
but there's one that's sort of the focus.
Yeah.
And so
With St. Augustine St. Augustine is not different than like St.
Irenae or or any other church father who talks about these events in that he sees one of them as being the central one
Right, and for him it's the exposure for paradise
Right, which then comes to kind of dominate Western Christian theology, right, but that is quoted quote by accident
meaning it meaning it's not that like St. Augustine is falling.
was went out and killed everybody who disagreed with something.
Right. Right. Right.
This is not like an engineered thing.
He was just the foremost
and most well written church father in Latin.
Yeah. Right.
And St. Augustine himself couldn't really read Greek.
And after him, almost no one could read Greek in the West.
Yeah. And so they ended up relying on him
and sort of he became the whole show.
And so all of these things that St. Augustine got.
wrong because everybody gets things wrong. Right? And St. Augustine was more humble and honest
than most humans in that he actually wrote the big book of retractions at the end of his life.
He retracted a lot of what he wrote and tried to get a publisher for that.
But like it like day Trinitate that everybody criticizes his work on the Holy Trinity,
he refused to republish it because he thought he got too much wrong in it. Okay, so
right? Like he was both.
more aware than anybody, right? He wouldn't have wanted Day Trinitata to become the Western
view of the Trinity, right? But it did, right? And so anybody who wants to bash St. Augustim himself
for that stuff doesn't understand how history works, right? But also I would add, if you tried to
base your whole Christian faith.
purely on the writings of one church father and each church father.
You're going to run into trouble. Yeah. Because there is no single church father
who is inerrant and perfect and never gets anything wrong and never is it odds with the rest
of the tradition or never fails to understand something, never omit something, right? That doesn't
exist, right? So I mean, pick a new example out of a hat.
If you base your whole faith on St. Gregory of Nissa,
you're gonna end up with an assorted view
of what Christianity is.
Not because there's something wrong with St. Gregory,
anything more than there's something wrong with St. Augustine.
Right, you could do that with St. John Chris Ostom.
You could do it with any one church father
and you would end up with a distorted view of Christianity
because that's not how Christianity works.
You don't like pick your favorite personality
and decide that he's right about everything.
Right.
Not to mention the fact that you're going to end up
Not knowing or saying anything about all the topics that author doesn't address
Yeah, right
So the other say this this idea of kind of emphasizing one or another aspect
It wasn't so much a debate like no, it's this no no, it's this you know
It was really just these are the things that are being emphasized by different church fathers right
Yeah, because they were they were
humans, right? And they thought about things and prayed about things. And they had, they
had actual ministries to actual other humans and actual places and actual times. And so when
they're preaching and writing, they're not just, we read church history like it's a bunch
of talking heads, you know, in this really idealist way, right? The reality is, you know,
St. John Chrysostom was dealing with actual situations, sometimes dire political situations.
in Antioch and in Constantinople.
Right, he's not just writing in this freeway
about systematic theology or something.
He's talking to particular problems
that particular people are having.
He's preaching to actual people
to help them with their actual lives.
Which I think is why, especially his work,
always seems so kind of fresh and present
because it's not ad hoc exactly,
but it is to the moment.
you know, yeah. Yeah, yeah. But all of it is that way. Yeah. Right.
Right. All of it is that way. When we read it is some kind of detached systematic theology
that could have been written at any time in any place, by any one, we're doing violence
to it. We're interpreting it incorrectly. Yep. Yep. So, but all that to say, yes. Yes.
Adam is not the figure in scripture who is primarily identified with the origin of
sinfulness.
as an archetypal sinner, as someone who's going to be on the wrong side of the last
judgment, that is not Adam, that is Kane who we're going to be talking about for the
rest of tonight, and the reason most folks in the West don't know that anymore is not
that's in Augustine's fault, per se.
Right, although his writings were involved.
Yeah, yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So I mean, and we should, and we should just say here at the
outset that the thing that Adam did was indeed a sin. Right? By identifying Cana's the
sinner, the primary sinner, we're not saying that what Adam did was not a sin. But the
word sin was not used for it. Yeah. They're in Genesis and Genesis. And we'll get into
that more detail in sin versus sins and all those kind of things. Yep. Yeah. That's our topic
to
I don't know where to go. Exactly. Exactly. So, Kane, where did he come from?
So, yeah, when that was the real problem, you know, in Genesis 4 was Adam. You know, he was
repenting for 40 days in the Jordan River according to the life of Adam and Eve. And Eve was off
raising cane.
If your way to it's everybody.
Thank you.
So we have to, yeah, we're gonna start by going through sort of the life of
Cain as we have it recorded in Scripture, which is not a ton, right?
There's not chapter after chapter about the life of Cain.
Heck, there's less than one chapter about the life of Cain, but we're going to go
through it because what we do know about Cain right away in Genesis chapter four
is important.
That gets dealt with and treated in certain ways in the New Testament,
And then...
also in certain ways in other second temple Jewish literature and in certain ways by
church fathers and other writers. But we have to start with what's in Genesis chapter
four. And so we start, we begin at the beginning, which is a very good place to start, which
is came being born. Right. And while some of you may be fortunate enough to not know why
we have to say this.
Cain in Genesis 4 is conceived and born in the usual way in which that happens.
But we should mention why some people... Well, we will. Yeah, it's the same.
Why do we have to say? We'll get to that. But yeah, yeah. It's exciting.
I mean, I think I speak for Father Andrew also that we are not going to be explaining to you what
the usual way is. Yes, right. If you don't know, ask your parents if you're an adult and you still
don't know, ask your priest. I'm gonna get angry, you know, some priests that I won't.
Yeah, but someone came to me and at yeah, no, but we have to say this because there are a couple
of different ways in which people want to say that cane may not have been the naturally
conceived and born son of Adam and Eve.
Yeah, there's this.
And it kind of runs, it kind of runs...
mostly in like Pentecostalist circles and Pentecostal adjacent circles, but not all of them by any means.
Not the majority. That's what they say. It should adjacent. Yeah, right. Yeah. I know I already got a lot
of them at it me, but no, I accused them all of believing this. Yeah, your average, your average
assembly of God pastor is not going to be teaching this. But there is this idea of something called the
serpents seed, which is this notion
that king is born of, let's say Adam is off somewhere and Eve has a moment with the serpent.
And so then that king is the son of the serpent.
Right.
And that's-
I eat the devil, right?
Yeah.
In a literal way.
Right.
The devil is literally his dad is this idea of the serpent seed.
And there's all kinds of just fanciful, crazy, I mean fun.
fun.
And for sure, although awful spin-offs from there about exactly what that means and the
origins of evil in the world.
And I strongly believe that this might be behind some of the ideas about reptilians in
high places and the government and that kind of stuff.
Well, hey, now don't tar that with the same brush.
You watch those videos of the Senate, framed by frame.
It's true.
There's little flickers and things.
...
And if you watch enough videos from the third eagle of the apocalypse on YouTube eventually,
you know, he'll sing it for you.
So there is another version of this that is differentiated by having, I guess, the veneer
of scholarship slathered upon it.
That is.
So mixing those metaphors, Father.
Yes.
So from everything, all the wonderful things
we say about the world of Old Testament scholarship
on this show, longtime listeners will not be surprised.
There's constantly this effort to find
what is behind the text.
So.
There's if there's a story in the text of especially the Torah, right?
Because we've chopped it all up in a little bit of bits, right?
There's a story in the Torah
then there's a real story behind it, right?
Story that's in the Torah is trying to cover up the story that's behind it.
Right, which is the real story, not the real story of the sense that it's true because of course old test
what's called don't think any of this stuff's true.
But uh, but
That's the original story, but the original story was too uki or weird or creepy to be allowed
to go on and had to be covered up.
So the hypothesis here is that the story of Adam knowing his wife, Eve, and her having
a son, right, that story, way too suspicious.
Right.
Why would they do that?
Why would they do hiding?
Yes.
What are they hiding?
The theory is that after Cain is born in Genesis 4, Eve says, I have received a son from
Yahweh.
Now all of us who are normal, well-adjusted people, who haven't spent seven or eight years
getting PhDs in art and 19th century Germans, hear that and say, she's thankful to God because
God gave her the gift of a son.
Right.
I'll see this.
kind of thing all the time. God gave us children. Yes. Right. But what these folks say is that
the story that's being covered up here, see this is where it's where it's where it sneaks out.
And the real story is that the original story is that Cain is actually Yahweh's son.
with you. Yeah, yeah. I mean, that just skips, you know, chapter four, verse one.
where it says, now Adam knew his wife.
That's part of the cover.
Yeah, oh, oh, excuse me.
It's all part of the cover.
Right, this is the same strategy.
People that do this all through.
Right.
And I get questions about this stuff.
Because they do the same thing.
Like, for example, the dedication of the first born
that pass over.
Oh, yes, right.
Right.
Child sacrifice.
Yeah, the same scholars say, yes,
this is covering up child sacrifice
that these are lights we're doing.
It's covering it up.
And so that they print these articles like,
oh, biblical evidence.
The evidence is the story that's in the Bible,
which clearly is covering up this other one supposedly.
Right?
biblical evidence of child sacrifice in Israel
and that people read that headline
and get upset and send me an email.
Right?
And so this is another one of those things.
I mean, I don't have much to say about it
other than that that is just an unbelievably stupid approach
to end.
right to reading any text right right just could complete herm a duet of
suspicion right could you imagine if every time someone sent you an email right
you know hey you want to go see a movie this Friday night what do you mean by
question does he not want me to ask he's trying to scrap me with the movie right
Like that, I mean, that's just not mentally healthy.
Right?
approach the world. But you know, you got to write journal articles and dissertations. So,
so very obviously in the text, the actual text that actually exists that you could actually
read, he is Adam's son. Right. And it's important in the narrative that he's Adam's son.
Yes. He's in Adam's image now, Adam post-expulsion from Paradise. Right. His story is going to be a
continue.
of Adam's story on a bad trajectory, right? Spoilers.
Keats, you haven't read the rest of the video.
Yeah, there may be one person listening
that has it read Genesis forever their life or heard the story.
But sorry about the spoilers.
We'll work through it anyway.
So the main sort of action that we see in the story of Kane
is start to unfold.
when he and his brother Abel,
his younger brother Abel go and offer sacrifices to God.
And we're told that Abel goes and offers an animal,
cane goes and offers some of his crops,
the fruit of the ground.
and Ables offering.
is accepted and Cain's offering is not.
And here's one of the first places where the train pulls into speculation station.
Yes.
Did he not offer the right stuff or did he not bake it correctly or God doesn't want the
vegetables he wants an animal because things have to die.
And this is, I know we've talked about it at the show but this is another good opportunity
again to point out.
especially in Genesis, but throughout the Bible, the way to approach the text is not to
come to it with a bunch of your questions that you're trying to answer to satisfy your
curiosity about different things, but to read the text and try to discover what the text
is saying.
Because I think if we read the text closely, we'll see why one was accepted and the other
wasn't.
Yeah, right.
But if you just sort of stop there,
Right, you can go all over with
Conjecture, right? So there's the yeah was he spoke was were they both supposed to be animals?
There are people some of our Protestant friends out there who base huge
Theological things on no it has to be an animal
Yeah, because it has to die
Right because it because it has to die and it can't be plants and then it's like yeah, but like we're in the Torah
There's plenty of offerings that are like first fruits
in grain offerings.
Right.
Offerings that God commanded.
Yeah.
Very explicitly.
It's not like he ever said, you know, do not bring me grain offerings and drink offerings.
I only want stuff that you have to kill before you bring it.
Yes.
Even some sin offerings were just wheat cakes.
Yeah.
If you read Leviticus closely, right?
But beyond that, we're not even told what kind of offering this was to be able to adjudicate
that, right?
It doesn't say it was a sin offering.
Let's see if it's a thank-offer-
If it was for first fruits, if it was for, I mean, right?
There's, yeah.
And there's no point, you know, in the three chapters prior, or in this chapter where
it says, and God commanded them to offer sacrifices, and this is how He said He should do it.
I mean, there's not even a point where He says that God is commanding a sacrifice.
You just see them doing it.
Right.
So the text gives us no way to assess.
I tell us nothing about the technique.
There's literally nothing about the technique.
Yeah.
right and offerings made and it doesn't give us any basis to judge what they should or shouldn't have been offering right so we we we
We can't do that right but
But we can look for example to where other places in the scriptures where this might be talked about and
One of those places that we're going to be coming back to sort of over and over and over again tonight
because
As I explained to Father Andrew yesterday, when you go and get a PhD, you learn more and more about less and less
until you know everything about nothing.
And so your knowledge of things is like this cone that comes down to a tiny point.
And so my tiny point is in like first John chapter 2.
So, first John chapter three that we're going to keep coming back to tonight is like really close.
to that. So if we keep coming back to first John 312, I can feel like I know what I'm talking about.
So this is just kind of a general warning, right? For anyone who wants to argue about first John with
you. Well, I suppose they have a lot of reading to do with the very latest open season on everything else.
Yeah. Yeah. Right. This is one of those things that people people tend to treat scholars,
sort of the way Marvel Comics treats scientists, right? Like if you're if you're in a Marvel
comic and your assigned.
like you can build an interdimensional portal.
That's what scientists do.
Make a chemical potion to shrink people.
You can do, like there's no particular science you've studied.
You just know science.
You can invent things and engineering you know too, apparently.
People treat scholars that way.
But the reality is being a scholar
means you know an incredible amount
about something very, very specific.
Right
Right. And so when you're talking about the further you get away from that specific thing,
the less you actually know as a scholar, right? So anytime a scholar is talking outside
his field, you should listen to it all because usually they'll say if a scholar is talking
outside of his field, it has the same value as a layman. I think it has less value than a layman
because we get pompous from having a PhD. And so we see we know more than we do.
Are you saying that Neil deGrasse Tyson may not be the person?
to listen to on philosophy and religion? Yes. Ed or Richard Dawkins. Ed or Sam Harris.
Right. Yeah. And I'm not the guy to listen to theoretical physics either. Right. But you have
a PhD, come on, I know I'm a scientist. So anyway, back to first or
our first time to first job, 3 verse 12, my comfort zone, my happy place.
We're actually here.
Here first we'll read 12 to 13, although it's 12, primarily that we're going to keep coming
back to.
Right, right.
Okay.
First John chapter three verses 12 and 13, we should not be like king, who was of the evil
one and murdered his brother.
And why did he murder him?
Because his own deeds were evil and his brother's righteous.
do not be surprised, brothers, that the
world hates you. Right. So these evil deeds of Canes, the evil deeds is not, he tried
to sacrifice some herbs to God. Right. Yeah, that's not an evil deed. No, there's no basis
to judge it. And it would be at most one deed. And this is deeds world. Right. So this
is talking about who these two people are. Right. Cane was already evil in doing evil deeds.
Right
and able was righteous and following God and doing good.
And so this is why when able then
went and offered a sacrifice to God,
God accepted it.
And when Cain, while still doing evil,
went and offered a sacrifice to God,
God did not accept it.
Yep.
Right.
Which I mean, we say we've seen this,
well, yeah, in the Old Testament,
we get this lots of times,
but probably the one that's the most memorable,
right is.
in Psalm 50, slash 51, where St. David says,
you know, you have to be contrite and humble before God.
And then you can offer Bullocks upon his altar,
like that's the last verse.
It's the character of your heart,
who you are is what makes a big difference
in the sacrifices.
It's not the only thing, right?
It's not like you can say, well,
I'm really humble before God,
So I don't have to do all these sag rights.
is that he commanded, it's a very important prerequisite.
You know, right?
And this has to be a major theme in the Old Testament.
And we see Israel not getting it in the Old Testament.
Yeah, over and over.
Because this is very different
than the way things work in the pagan world.
In the pagan world, the whole job
of various kinds of priests
is to know how to do the rituals correctly.
Yeah, they're professional ritualists.
You go and you offer the sacrifice
And you may call the...
cuts correctly and you read the Ed Trails correctly, you do all the stuff correctly, and
if you do it all correctly, then the God accepts the sacrifice and does what you want.
Yeah, it's about skill.
And if you mess it up somewhere, then it doesn't work.
But that's not how, yeah, way the God of Israel works.
Right?
And that's why over and over again in the Old Testament, right, it's that God desires,
mercy and not sacrifice, right Ed?
At certain points, he tells Israel to stop offering the sacrifices because they're not repenting
and living completely wickedly but then following the instructions from Leviticus about killing
animals. Yeah and and and and you don't see that in paganism. Yeah, you know, you know, like
you okay, look you guys you did the offering correctly, but you know your hearts were messed up
when you came to the second like Thor never shows up and says that. It's just gimme.
right now it's the exact top
it. It's a top of it. Like you look at when Rome lost the legion to Arminius in Germany.
And the people were mad because they're like, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
They were like, we did all this stuff we were supposed to do. We were not supposed to get beaten.
And so this for years after that, they would throw rocks at the temples in Rome.
Yeah, because the God had swindled them. Yeah, the God has kept up their end in the bargain, right?
That's how that worked in the pagan world, right? But it Israel God saying look I don't-
I don't want, I don't delight the blood of bulls and goats, right?
Yeah, I don't need that stuff.
That's not the point, right?
Right.
It's supposed to be an expression.
And so if it's not going to be an expression of repentance, an expression of love, an expression
of praise, an expression of thanksgiving, then just knock it off, man.
Save your time.
Yeah, it's hypocrisy then, which is worse than not doing it all.
Yeah.
And this carries over, right, even in the New Testament when Christ says, if you're on your
way to the altar, right?
realize someone has something again.
you, leave your gift, go find them and be reconciled first.
Exactly.
Then come back and make your offering.
So this is a basic biblical principle and that's what we're getting laid out here in
Genesis 4 already.
And if you read Genesis 4.7, for example, very closely, this is part of where God comes
and talks to Kane after the sacrifice incident. He pretty much says that.
Right. Right. Yeah. In verse seven, I mean, it starts out with verse six. The Lord said to
King, why are you angry and why is your face fallen? Then he says to him, if you do well, this is
the ESV. If you do well, will you not be accepted? Yeah. Right. The Hebrew there is literally do good.
Yeah. If you do good, if you do good, will you not be accepted? Right. So he's telling
can't what the problem was. If you repent and you start to do good, if you turn your
life around, I will accept your offerings. Right. He's not rejecting cane as a human. Right.
He's rejecting the offering because it's not being offered to him with a with a pure heart.
Right. Um, yeah. So let's say this goes back to the idea of, I mean, we've talked about
this a bunch of times, but what is sacrifice? It's about hospitality. If you're, you know,
down to do hospitality with someone that you've been horrible towards.
kind of meal is that, you know?
And you're still not so big about him
like at the table while he's there.
Right, yeah, yeah.
I mean, we have to remember that,
that you don't sit down and eat a meal
with someone that you're on terrible terms with.
That just doesn't, I mean, you do it.
It does happen sometimes, but wow, awkward.
And maybe even offensive.
Yeah.
And if part of the purpose of that meal
is reconciliation, sitting there insulting him
and his wife while you're doing it
is not a good way to go.
about that, right? You're better off probably not inviting them over if that's what you're
going to do. Right. I mean, and that's that's the logic behind what God says when he rejects
sacrifices. Yeah. So as you mentioned there, right? So notice again, God doesn't and this
is the proof that God isn't rejecting Cain as a human, right? Because after he rejects
the offering and Cain's angry and upset, God comes to him. Right, it talks to him.
and tries to help him, right?
He doesn't write him off.
He doesn't say good.
You were never one of the elect anyway.
He comes to him and talks to him and says,
what we just said, and then he says,
something very important that we're now
going to kind of dissect.
He says, sin is crouching at your door.
It's desire, well, somebody put up your translation
in the notes.
Right.
It desires to master you, but you must master it.
Yeah, right.
It's sort of what the Hebrews has.
If you do not do the good, sin is crashing in the door.
So it's dependent upon the way he acts.
Yeah.
You know, and then it wants to master him
and God says, you gotta get control over this.
Yeah.
It's gonna control you, dude.
And so I'm pretty sure we've mentioned it
on the ship.
before, but the word that's translated crouching there, right, is, and it's in Hebrew, it's the word
Rovates, but that is derived from an Akkadian word that refers to a certain type of demon that was
believed to crawl up through cracks in the ground and sort of prowl around. And like jump on people,
right? Yeah. That's great. Every time I think of it.
So the idea is, the idea is that sin, and notice sin here is singular, right?
It's not sins.
It's not breaking a bunch of rules is crouching at your, right?
That's not how sin is being talked about here.
It's sin.
As we talked about, like, it's the sort of demonic beast.
It's a monster.
There's a monster at your door prowling around.
It's getting ready to jump on you, right?
And it's going to want to, you must master it.
You're going to have to struggle with it.
You'll have to fight it.
right? When it comes for you, you're going to have to find it. And so it's portrayed
as this sort of demonic power, right? And this isn't just this one weird place, right,
in Genesis 4. This is going to be the primary way that St. Paul, for example, talks about
sin. There are a handful of cases where St. Paul uses sins plural, where when he
says, sins plural, he's talking about offenses. Right. He more often uses the word
transgressions for those things, but sometimes there's a sample cases where he uses sins.
Usually St. Paul uses sin in the singular. And he's he's thinking of it in the same
way as a power or a force in the world, right, that seeks mastery over us. And that
that we have to master, right?
Of course, a famous passage that has that language in it is when he says, you know, all
things are permissible to me, but not all things are beneficial.
All things are permissible for me, but I will not be mastered by anything.
Because that is active versus passive thing again.
Right.
And we talked about this last time a little bit, right?
This is that same kind of view of sin, sort of as this force.
Every time I talk about this in terms of cane,
somebody, not the same somebody.
I'm not referring to one person. There's always somebody. It's always a different somebody. It's a certain man
Well
We'll say well, what about Romans 5 verse 12?
Right therefore just as sin came into the world through one man and death through sin so death spread to all men because I'll sin
Yes, and my immediate response is what about Romans 5 verse 12
And explain yourself
I stare at them intimidatingly.
No. So, right. And so this is obviously the one man is talking about Adam. And it's talking about
the relationship of sin and death. But notice, he says, sin, singular, just as sin, came into the world
through one man. Yeah. So that one man is the door. Right. So Adam is like the door that let sin into
into the world because in Genesis 4,
since already out there prowling around in the world.
looking for Kane. Yeah, right. It's looking for Kane. Kane doesn't let it into the world.
Right. His dad did that. Yeah. So it's in the world now. Right. But
Kane is the person who we're going to see spoilers again. That's the first person who's sin masters.
Sin ceases and who's sin masters. And takes control of not his father, even though his father is how
how he came into the world.
And so, again, St. Paul could say what he wants to say.
And so since he's using sin in the singular there,
he's sort of deliberately giving that perception.
Because he could have said, he could have used a participle.
He could have said, therefore just his sinning began in the world with one man.
Right? If he wanted to talk about breaking rules and Adam
Right, it's the beginning of sinning.
and that.
And so there's a lot of ways he could have said it, but this is what he actually said.
And then death comes into the world, right?
Also through Adam, right?
And spreads to everyone as all, now notice there, St. Paul says, sinned, there he uses the
verb.
Right?
So there he's talking about a person taking an action.
is not talking about the force out in the world.
Yeah, and we don't really have time to go into the complicated relationship between
sinning and death and sin the
the force, the demonic force. I almost wish we had just capitalized that, although that's the name of a desert,
isn't it? The desert of sin. And a Roman Catholic cardinal. I remember when Cardinal Sin was the Cardinal
of the Philippines. That was, wow, Cardinal Sin. Cardinal Sin sounds like a villain in one of those bad
Christian comics right?
No, but apparently I don't think I should.
Not the other ones.
Oh man.
That brings me back.
But yeah, the cardinal of the Philippines for a while was Cardinal Sin.
I would, I'm sure in whatever his native people's language was,
which I don't know if it was Tagalog or not, Sin was not the same thing as it is English,
but yeah, it is kind of complicated.
Maybe we'll get into that in a future episode.
What is the relationship between sinning death?
and sin, capital S. But that's kind of not what this is about.
But in any event, we should just know that it doesn't work
in a kind of mechanical way.
If you do this, then this will happen, right?
If you sin this amount, then you're going to die.
That's not what's going on here.
And also that there are different ways
that gets talked about in various parts
of the Orthodox traditions.
So it's OK.
If it's a little bit muddy at this point,
maybe we'll cover it in the future.
But for now, before we get...
to the end of this first half.
We've got Kuneiform to read.
Yeah, right.
There's Kuneiform here in our notes.
I can't read it, but it looks pretty cool.
So we'll move on that.
So there's this dialogue where God is almost pleading with
Cain not to go down the path that he's been going down
and that he's now about to go past the point of no return.
Yeah, it's almost like a father.
saying don't do drugs. It's going to kill you, dude. Yeah, you know,
so it's a little more serious because yeah, way more serious. Yeah. So
spoilers again, Kane kills his brother, murders his brother. And then in response to that,
he receives a curse and the language is deliberately comes into the state of curse and
and the language is deliberately reminiscent of the curse.
that his father Adam came under in the previous chapter in Genesis 3 at the
expulsion from Paradise.
Yes. I mean, if you read these chapters together, you'll immediately see this
kind of language repeated and it'll be clear that there's this parallel.
But there's also this sort of intensification, right?
When you compare Keynes to his situation to his dad situation.
So remember in Genesis 317, Adam is told that cursed is the ground because of
view.
It's a result of what Adam had done now.
The ground was under a curse.
Whereas, Cain is told you are cursed from the ground.
So instead of the ground being cursed, that from,
there's this separation now between Cain and the earth.
And the result of that, for Adam, the result of that,
in Genesis 3, was that he was going to have to bring
food from the ground by the sweat of his brow by hard manual labor there's
gonna be thorns and pistols there's gonna be difficulty and struggle for him
to bring food out of the earth with cane in Genesis 4 verse 12 it's not
happening right he's not gonna be able to bring food out of the ground at all
he's gonna be unable to farm unable to sustain himself from the earth right and
So there
was in paradise. Remember, they're told they can eat from the fruit of any tree. Right? So,
they didn't even have to kill plants. Yeah, just pick the fruit. The rest of the creation offered
itself to Adam and Eve for nourishment. Right? Offered the fruit for nourishment. They just had to
walk by and pluck it off the tree. Right? Adam has to now go and work the ground.
to bring forth that food, right?
And came now is cut off from the rest of creation in a way
that the rest of creation will not sustain him.
Yeah, isn't there, I can't remember,
if this image of the ground being like bronze
or something like that, I can't remember.
That's in Deuteronomy.
That's in Deuteronomy, yeah.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
In the layout of the curse,
but it's the same kind of curse,
the state of curse is the same kind of thing
we're talking about.
Yeah.
So this raises the question within the narrative of Genesis 4.
Okay, how is Kane gonna survive?
Right?
And he's got two main problems.
Problem number one, he killed his brother.
Able is the first human to die.
Right.
He's got this horrible thing.
Parents, if nobody else, are probably gonna want revenge.
Right?
potentially other children in the
and you could want revenge, right?
So he's not, so Cain's not safe anywhere
from sort of the cycle of violence
that he's now kicked into motion.
And then secondly, how's he gonna survive
in terms of how's he gonna eat?
Yeah, right.
Is God just cursing him to be, to stop to death here?
Yeah.
So these two aspects of that problem
of that problem get dealt with in two different ways.
So the way in which that cycle of vengeance is dealt with is dealt with by what has been
traditionally called the Mark of Cain.
This is the part of the program where we get to talk about how stupid racists are.
It's true, everybody, and I don't feel bad about using these words, racist idiots, because
Hey, if you want to send an email to H.F.F. defending racists, send it to Father Ann.
through Damon at hfethradio.com.
That's an instant.
We need to take on racist.
But so there have been at various points, folks, trying
to justify racism from the Bible.
And what of the, I mean, every way they've tried to do it
is stupid.
But this is the stupidest by saying that the mark of Cain
something to do
with the color of cane skin being different.
Right, which there's nothing in the text that suggests that at all, like it's just zero.
But more importantly, if you actually, I don't know, if you can read, right?
So that's step one of why most races probably didn't see this problem.
You can't read.
If you continue reading you get to Genesis 6 through 9.
in just a few chapters, when everyone except knowing his sons is wiped out by the flood.
Yeah. That's everybody descended from Kane.
Right. So there's not a cane race around everybody.
Yeah, there's no one descended from Kane around.
So that's why I mean, it's on the face stupid.
So yeah, hopefully none of you had that in your head.
Many of you.
had probably heard about it. And it belized belief that there were people who believed that. But
that is a big, uh, negativity. So, um, but as Father Andrew said in the text, there's not even
anything that really tells us that this is some kind of physical mark. Yeah, right.
Right, this is like a cowlick in his hair or something, right? Like,
because because first of all I mean that wouldn't really make
makes sense either right because like if the whole point is he says anybody who sees
me will kill me and God says okay well I'll make you really identifiable that'll solve
the problem right again right that doesn't really that doesn't really work.
So the word here in Hebrew that's translated in Mark is Oat.
And that is a word...
that means a pledge or a witness or an oath.
And yes, we looked it up.
This is not an opportunity for Father Andrew's
apology corner.
Oath and Oath are not cognate.
They are.
Even though Oath means oath.
Yes.
Right.
They are false friends.
False friends.
So, yeah.
And so this is like a pledge.
And the point is God makes this promise to Cain.
pledge that anyone who harms him, right, it will be God who avenges him. Yeah. So it's Mark
in the English sense of like, Mark this well, which is a sort of archaic way of speaking, right? But
if you read the books that we do, you get this all the time. Mark this well. Pay attention. He will
mark Cane and that he's going to keep an eye on him, right? Right. Right. Where of what happens? Right.
Right, exactly.
And this is also the beginning of a...
theme, right? Notice God says the way you end the cycle of violence is God says I will deal with it.
Right. Yeah. And this is the beginning of God being the one who silences the Avenger and ultimately
vengeance is mine says the Lord. Right. God takes care of breaking the cycle of violence. So that
That takes care of that part of cane-wurring about being hunted.
So then the next part is how is he going to live and that solved by the founding of a city?
Yeah, he set up a system and
You can live off of what other people do
Yeah, right and so there's going to be now commerce there's going to be these other things that are going to allow him
To survive without being able to live in a Grian
Lifestyle so the city that is mentioned here
found it in the land of
nod. Yes. Yes. Is an actual city. So there's a little bit of
unclarity in the way that the Hebrew is translated sometimes. A
better translation of it for various reasons. You'll often hear
it translated a way that makes it sound like Cain named the city
after his son, Enoch. Right. So shouldn't the city be called
Enoch. Right, but it's Cain actually named names the city after Enoch's
So
on, IRAD is how it's spelled in most English transliterations.
That's IRAD.
Okay.
And that is the city of Eradu, which is the southern Sumeria.
Yeah, I mean, if you listen to it, right, it's got the vowels are a little bit different,
but it's still got the same consonants of R and D, IRAD, Eradu, you can hear the similarity,
I hope everybody.
Yeah.
Right. It's...
it's Eridu and Father Andrew, do you want to describe the
Kuneiform to be? Oh yes, so there's actual Kuneiform in
our notes. Thanks. Fun with fonts, ladies. Yeah, right,
exactly. So the first Kuneiform character, pictogram, you see
four spiky things, pointing downwards, with one across it,
moving from left to right.
And then next to all those, there's a big one going from top to bottom, right?
And then the second character is four of those marks pointing right,
and then they're surrounded by a diamond-shaped box of four other marks, you know,
so basically a square, but turned on one of its points, right? So those are the two images that
you get from the Q&A form. That's about as good as I could do. I'm sure there's some official
I'm just describing this but I don't know it.
I was just curious.
is how you do it.
I'm glad you got it.
Well, there you go.
Spiky things.
Sash marks.
Little wedges.
Yeah.
Wedges, right?
So we don't need no stinky wedges.
That Sumerian name is Pradau's Nunkie Eraduke.
And the Akkadian, which is northern Mesopotamia, Semitic language, called it Eritu.
uh...
Eradue
It was considered in the ancient Near East in a lot of places at a lot of times, not everywhere at
all times, but maybe even most places at most times to have been the first city. We now know it
actually isn't, archaeologically. But this is the tradition about it. It's not even the first
Sumerian city archaeologically, but they believed it was at the time. Right. And so the idea here is that
Genesis 4.
is as we've seen time and time again, it's sort of interacting with the traditions of Israel's
neighbors, right? In terms of, right? So, for example, the Sumerian king lists, right, in many,
but not all of them, Eridu is the first city. And the founding of Eridu is this because it's the
the first city is this incredibly important event in the history of civilization.
So the the kingship comes down from heaven for the first time in
Eradu and their first king is Al-ulim who lives like 28,000 years. And he has as
we've talked about before, what we talked about the Epochalo, when we talked about
giants, he has a sage in Epochalo, right, this divine being named Adapah, who
advises him, right, and brings civilization.
in the city. We have other Sumerian material that talks about Enke who was the God of the city,
founding the city. Enke was believed to have brought up the city and all life in the world for
for that matter out of what now the Persian Gulf,
up out of the seas to the south.
Inc. He was believed to live in the far waters. His temple in Eridu was an aquifer
Which wow, that's crazy, but just consider the maintenance on that yes like it's always wet
Man I live in Louisiana man. Yeah, right exactly
Prepetual flooding
That's what we want we want it flooded
but this isn't just right
when Eradu is sort of this big prominent Sumerian city early on, much later in the Neobabalone
and Empires.
We're talking about like Nebuchadnezzar.
We're talking about thousands of years later.
The Babylonians still believed that Eradu was the first city.
They just, of course, said it was founded by Marduk there.
Yeah, they're a guy.
They're a guy.
But so at the time of the Babylonian exile, that would have been the view of the city of
So Genesis 4 is saying, again, this is sort of correcting the record.
This was not a great moment in civilization.
This was not when the divine came to earth.
This is Cain murdered his brother.
He's the first murderer.
He's the first great sinner.
He had to go on the lamb and he built this city.
It's like a hideout to try and survive because he couldn't farm.
So you can see how that inverts.
the whole view of human civilization.
Yeah, right.
Right.
Sort of in one fell swoop in a few verses here in Genesis 4.
And for the record, Eridu was founded around 5400 BC.
And this was one of those a lot of times on the show when we give very ancient dates.
We know there are certain folks in our listener base who don't like dates that go beyond a certain
point.
But the great thing here is 5,400 BC works either way.
So regardless of your view of things, 5,400 BC,
pounding of Aridu, it even works for Kane
on certain people's timelines.
So, yeah.
And so that sort of comparative condemnation
of city life versus nomadic.
agricultural life is a theme that runs through Genesis and through most of the old
Testament. And we've talked about that at various points. Yeah. Yeah, this
idea that civilization is not the result of a divine endowment but is actually
the outgrowth of sin. Someone running from God. Right. Right. And moving to say,
you know, when Abram and Lot separate the land, right? Abram, of course.
wants to live nomatically on the plane. Lot's like, oh, let me go hang out there down by Sodom and Gomorrah.
It seemed like fun happening in places.
Right. You want to go to the city.
Right. Kind of regrets leaving Ura in the first place maybe.
Yeah, so there's a very different
perception here. Yeah, exactly, exactly.
All right, well, that is the end of our first half of tonight's episode of The Lord of Spirits.
We're gonna take a quick break and we'll be right
back. Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take
your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-A-F-Radio.
New from Ancient Faith Publishing. Secret Turning. A collection of short stories
Bye.
I, Stephen, signari.
So I'm out in the lot of little heaven, and up comes father known from behind.
grabs me, gives me a kiss, and tells me he's happy to see me.
Wherein is worn out, dungery bib overalls with the beat up straw stetson, pulling his
wire basket, going shopping on the avenue.
How old is now him anyway, Sharky asked.
Older than he acts, lefty said.
who be ready said yeah, and younger than he seems.
So he says to me, Theodery, the church is much better when you're there.
It's not the whole family when we don't see you.
You know, God misses His children, and none older misses her son.
Now available in paperback, eBook and audiobook at store.inchantfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-2--
That's 855 AF radio.
Back.
This is the second half of Lord of Spirits.
We're talking about Cain, walking the earth, sin, all that stuff.
This is the second part of the show.
And as the voice of Steve just said, you can call us at 855 AF radio.
Again, that's 855-237-2346.
I have no commercial for this half.
Well, if...
If you wanted to be the new CEO of Ancient Bay, I'm a head.
I missed past you by.
That's true.
That's right.
Applications are closed, everybody.
Can I have to wait a few decades for the next guy to retire?
It's true.
Yeah.
So all right.
Well, we've got keen having founded the city and
civilization begins, right?
Yes.
Yeah.
Yeah, so unlike
came from Kung Fu. He will not be walking the earth anymore. He will be in a city.
So this half, our second half, we're going to sort of start looking at the figure of
Cain as he develops in sort of later writings. Right. So in Second Temple Judaism
and some of the church fathers in the New Testament.
How?
is the figure what is the figure of Kane sort of his legacy? How does it function? Why is he important?
Right because again as we talked about post legacy of St. Augustine for a variety of reasons in
the West, Kane doesn't get talked about that much. There's not a lot of there's not a lot of Kane.
But lots of people were talking about Kane and second-temple Judaism.
more people were talking
about Kane than we're talking about Adam.
Yeah, and I mean, it's interesting that Kane does show up a lot in in other kinds of I
don't want to call it legendary material, but like a lot of stories, for instance, here,
I'll throw out the obligatory Beowulf reference.
Beowulf references Kane, you know, Grendel, the monster of the big monster at the beginning
of this story.
And suddenly I'm reminded of that Sesame Street book called The Monster at the end of
this book but but beautiful
does have a monster at the end of the book and it's a it's a hidden dragon. But see there
you go. But but Grandola said to be a descendant of Kane and it also says that Kane is the father
of of orcs and of all kinds of evil giants and and elves elves are bad creatures in Beowulf.
I'm afraid mostly. So it's not creatures in everything. Yeah. Yeah. Right. I mean fantasy
world elves are responsible for everything that that's true even in
Tolkien. A lot of the bad stuff gets really started because of one particular elf named
fan or. They do. They really do. But yeah, I mean, Kane is a big deal in, like especially
the medieval imagination. He shows up all the time. Yeah. He is this figure. He is this figure.
that disjunction with Adam is important because as we mentioned on the show
before we see in the icon of the heroine of hell the raising up of Adam and Eve, right?
Yeah.
Don't see the salvation of Cain, the repentance of Cain.
Right.
That's not who Cain is.
Yeah.
And in a lot of all scenes icons, you see Adam and Eve.
And in many cases, they have halos showing that they are among the divine counsel, but
you don't see Cain.
Cain's not there.
Yeah.
So yeah, we're gonna sort of trace that.
where that talk about Kane comes from.
So, Kane is an example of something.
He's not just the first, he's also the worst.
So, one of the places that he's talked about,
that is in your New Testament, if you are in your Old Testament,
if you're Orthodox or Roman Catholic,
in your new testament if you live in the second century.
but is in the book of wisdom in chapter 10 verses 3 and 4. Yeah, which goes like this. But when
the unrighteous went away from her and we should say that her is wisdom, right, that's if you read
early in the chapter, you get that. But when the unrighteous went away from her in his anger,
He perished also in the fury wherewith he murdered his brother.
for whose cause the earth being drowned with the flood,
wisdom again preserved it and directed the course of the righteous
in a piece of wood of small value.
That's a really great way of referring to the ark.
Yeah, it's cheap.
A piece of wood, a small value.
How much for go for wood these days?
I don't know.
So, you notice here,
Cain is just referred to as the unrighteous. Right? The unrighteous.
one. Right. And interestingly, Wisdom wants to note that Cain also perished when in his
anger he murdered his brother. And that's talking about a little bit what we talked about
last time, that that idea of spiritual death of being cut off from God, from which then
sort of furthering the crosses sets in, right?
And so.
one perishes physically later on. And then also Cain, and this is going to be one of
the major themes in terms of how Cain is seen, is that he sort of sets things in motion
that will end up causing the flood. Right? The flood, because the flood is going to come
to purify the creation from humanity.
So at the time of the flood, we're at everyone's thought was always evil all the time,
right, which is worse than me, because some of my thoughts are not evil once in a while,
at least.
But this is always evil all the time.
Everything has snowballed up to that point, but that begins with Cain, right?
That begins with Cain allowing himself to be mastered by evil.
So Joe C. Fess.
is going to he refers he uses the word
uh
paneroetitos which is not the same as potatos
only wrote them
mash them stick them in the stew
means most evil yeah right yeah so he's not just the evil one or the other
righteous one he's the most evil one yeah like at the end of the Lord's prayer you've got
they were Ponyru, the evil one. Ponyru tatos is like...
This is a... yes.
most evil one. Right, so yeah, Joseph, yeah, he the most evil one, but he's also a teacher of evil.
Like he is, he is a great evil, and it's, and so not only has he been sort of mastered by sin,
but now through him, sin is mastering others as he's making it wearer.
He's making it wearer. He's leading people into evil.
Yeah, so we've got this quote from Josephus' antiquities. This is chapter one,
translated by a very Victorian gentleman.
Yes, 59 to 6. I know when I was reading this is like I really feel like I need to say however
He did not accept of his punishment in order to amendment
Because that's how it reads anyway. I won't do that. I fake fake Victoria an accent
You get to use after a sentence and a half it does it kind of does and then you like it only gets really interesting if you do sort of like a grand
Mofftarkin thing
Then it's becomes compelling and nasty but in our moment of trial
So, okay, so here's Josephus. However, he did not accept of his punishment in order to amendment,
but to increase his wickedness for he only aimed to procure everything that was for his own bodily pleasure,
though it obliged him to be injurious to his neighbors. He augmented his household substance with much wealth
by rapine and violence, or rapine, I'm not sure actually how that's usually used.
He was repeating in violence, he excited his acquaintance to procure pleasure and spoils by robbery.
Wow, and became a great leader of men into wicked courses. He also introduced a change in that way of simplicity
wherein men lived before and was the author of measures and weights. And whereas they lived innocently and generously while they knew nothing of such arts,
he changed the world into cunning craftiness. He, first of all, said boundaries about lands, which doesn't mean borders, I guess, but is more like
Dede, spying and selling...
really stopperity markers. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
So that land will be bought and sold. Yeah. Yeah. Cause there are not nation states in 5400 BC.
This is whatever it is. So this is Josephus in the antiquities. Right. And notice the point
he makes about Kane. Kane does not repent. Right. So even Josephus sees based on the way of the story
the way that God speaks to came, that ye-
Even the curse that befalls Cain, just like the curse that befalls his father, was there
to drive him to repentance, but Cain does not repent.
It was not purely punishment.
It was to bring him to repentance, which he refused.
And rather than returning in repentance, he chooses to pursue all of his own pleasures.
So he just lets sin take over.
and ever desire comes to him, he allows.
to control him. And then he leads others into it. But then also, you notice he sort of related
to the city. This is where Josephus is getting this. This is related to the founding of
the city. That before this, right, people had lived in this way of simplicity where they
lived together, they shared things, right? Everybody contributed what they could to the family,
to the community and everyone supported each other for help.
Which is what came.
could have done, right? If your question is, well, if he can't farm, how could he support himself?
Well, he could have returned to his parents and repentance, right?
Yeah.
He didn't have to be the one doing the farming. He could have done other things to contribute to the community, right?
And people provide food for him. But that's not how he chooses to go about it.
He goes about it the opposite way, right? He chooses to go and use violence and take and steal, right?
and then to put it place these means of commerce and these means of...
of cunning craftiness.
It's a system very much.
Right, a system where you're able to exploit others,
take advantage of others,
do everything except honest work with your hands,
right, in order to extract and receive
sort of bodily pleasure.
Right?
And so this is who can is.
And this understanding of communal life
is why you know,
at the beginning of the book of Acts,
when it talks about the early Christian community in Jerusalem,
it talks about them having everything in common
and living together in common, right?
And then you get the folks who as soon as they're done reading
and have to explain, now this is not communism, right?
This is the beginning of Acts is referring to this idea.
is referring to this idea.
communal life with the family.
Yeah, it's referring to this.
That is the type of life that the early Christians return to.
Right, they pulled out of the life of this, even the city of Jerusalem, right, which had
become horribly corrupt as we know, right?
By the time of Christ, and many times before and after, they had retreated from that to
go back to this kind of simplicity of life.
the reference there in Acts that they're trying to show us.
way of life that was sort of more gods intent from the beginning. Right? So not only does he do all
this stuff, right? But he's also presented very frequently as the first heretic. Yeah, which is
interesting. You wouldn't think like wait. Is Cain violating some kind of crystallological dogma or
What does that mean exactly? You know an anti-traditarian. Yeah, he's a blanket.
Let's try to work righteousness, man. Gotta stop it off-king. No.
So he's referred to it this way in a bunch of places, right? In Filo, in two of the
the targum that we call neophyte and pseudogenathon.
Clement of Alexandria uses it in this way.
or Talian uses them in this way. But more importantly, he's used twice this way in the Bible
once in Jude verse 11 because there's no chapters in Jude. It's a paragraph. And once in
here we are again, verse John 3. Welcome back.
In both of those places, these false teachers or sort of heretical groups that have come into
to the church.
and our leading people astray
and our afflicting the church are compared to Cain.
Directly.
They become like Cain, they follow Cain.
And the way that works is if you look at in both cases,
what these people are doing,
these people are coming into the Christian community
and exploiting people in order to gratify their own desires.
Yeah, which, I mean, not to put too fine a point on it,
But there are people at our time.
who will try to divide out certain kinds of dogma
from morality and ethics, especially sexual morality.
Even people who, you know,
their voices are from within the Orthodox Church.
And as you like to say, that dog will not.
You know, this sense of gratifying your desires,
being associated with false teaching.
And of course, as we see many times in scripture
with idolatry.
means that, yeah, morality is not like up for grabs.
Especially sexual morality.
Right.
Yes, always intertwined in this way.
And this is why it is a general truth worthy of acceptance
that all cults eventually become sex cults.
Right.
I mean, I've spent, because I have a weird little interest
in this, I've spent a lot of time reading about new religious
Movements is-
especially various kinds of cults and sects.
And they do.
I mean, they head in that direction, almost to a man.
And it's always men.
It's always men running these things.
You know, taking advantage, dominating women,
dominating whoever comes within their orbit.
Right.
They get power and they want to sacri,
and they want to indulge all of their desires.
Yep.
Yeah.
The power they get through these heretical communities,
then used to do that.
And they are like Cain in that regard, right?
Yeah.
So, now we're going to say some more nice stuff about St. Augustine, because of course, Cain
is a major figure in the city of God, right?
Because the whole premise, so St. Augustine writes the city of God as the Western Roman Empire
is collapsing.
And he, one of his major in a-
intellectual contributions there is the idea of the secular, which is not the same as what we now call secular.
No.
But the word secular in Latin, before that, had just referred to a period of time, right?
Like an age or an era, right?
And what St. Augustine does is he uses Seculum Truff.
to, and he's mingling some Plato in here as his want, that there's this realm of becoming,
there's this realm of this world that is always shifting and changing, it's always sort of
temporarily determined and in flux, and that's the secular, that's the city of man.
And so for him, Genesis 4 is Cain founding the city of man.
And you hear about this in city of God 1517 is where he talks about
Cain in particular, but
So does that world of change and then over against that there is the city of God
Yeah, the New Jerusalem which is eternal which is unchanging right and so
St. Augustine writes writes the city of God which is
epically huge and covers
Everything in the world right but
The thrust is he's trying to say
to people who literally their world is crumbling around them.
Yeah, right.
In ways that fortunately, I mean, who knows?
In the United States at least, the way things are going.
But we thankfully have not had most of us listening,
have not had to experience yet.
But I mean, we're talking about, you know, one day,
people on horses come into your town
and just start murdering and raping people, right?
House to house.
Yeah, and the authorities are crumbling. Yeah, there's no food in the market
And people are starving right this is the reality of the fall of the Western Roman Empire
Okay, this is the world they're living in and St. Augustine is writing to them and saying this is the way of the world
Yeah, city of man and Rome was the city of man. It never stays
Hey, but not the eternal city
No, there is another city to which you belong
And that is unchanging, and that is pure.
But so, you not only sets up this paradigm with Cain as the founder of this city of man,
but he points to in 1517, not the year, sorry Lutherans.
Ah, city of God, book 15.
Section 17. He points to the two genealogies of Seth and Cain, right? And he
takes, he treats these genealogies as in a way that's actually reminiscent of
of wisdom literature. It's got to clever thing he does. To be these two ways, these
two paths that a person can pursue. And he points to the seventh generation of
of each of the
genealogies, right, as being sort of because it's the seventh and seventh you get
reach completion. Right. That's the end of the road. That's the fullness. That's the end of the road
where this road leads. So if you do that with Seth, right, the genealogy of Seth, the seventh from
Adam is of course, Enic. Right. Who gets to take it up into heaven? Yeah, assumed up into heaven.
walks with God was more theosis right that we talked about last time.
You look at Seth's or you look at Keynes' genealogy and the seventh is Lammak, who's the
one who sings the song to his two wives about how great he is and how he's going to murder
anybody who messes with him and doesn't need God to avenge him.
Yeah, so he's the super murderer, you know, yeah, right exactly.
And it's interesting to me actually that...
I mean, we see this in Revelation, of course,
but then there's this theme also persists in other places,
as well that it's what's held in contrast
ultimately against the city of man
is not the untrammeled wilderness.
It's another city, it's the city of God.
As it says, we have here no continuing city,
but we seek the one that is to come, right?
And so there's this idea that civilization
is ready.
But it's only because God sends it only because God makes it happen. You know the cane city is not gonna is not it
You just know no salvation. Yeah, and polishing it won't help
Right putting you know having having less crime in it won't help
Right, right less less obvious crime less of the crimes we don't like
You know even spray painting Bible verses on the walls is it good?
is it ultimately going to help?
Right?
Yeah, and so then as those are understood, right, as those figures are sort of the culmination
of the sort of this anti-Christ figure, right?
Lamic has these sons then in the genealogy.
And those sons are treated not so much as a continuation of the genealogy as they are
treated as sort
of based on the contributions they make to civilization, they are treated as sort of divisions
of the types of sin and wickedness that sort of come out of Kames Line or come upon you
and take you over as you go down that road.
This road that Kame began, right, started traveling.
And they're each described as being with a father of certain, you know,
way of living or skill really is what it comes down to. So this is Genesis chapter 4 verses 21
23-22
Adub or J. Ball. He was the father of those who dwell in tents and have livestock. So you've got
keeping
Keeping livestock. Verse 21, his brother's name was Jubal. He was the father of all those who play the Lyre and Pipe
music. And then verse 22, Zilla also bore tubal cane. He was the forerger of...
all instruments of bronze and iron and the sister of Tublecane was Naama. So you've got, you know,
husbandry, you've got music and you've got metallurgy. Yes. And that's about music.
Right. And so, so what's going on these are the livestock thing, right? This livestock is
is food livestock. Right? Right.
Right? So nobody has permission to eat meat yet in Genesis 4.
But more importantly, they're making a contrast in sort of the movement.
Right? Where again, as we said, said before, in paradise, you know, the trees are
offering their fruit to Adam and Eve for nourishment.
Then Adam's having to work the ground.
Now they're going out and killing.
Right? They're going out fighting killing, killing things, right?
to feed their own desires.
right. And this has to do with sort of the the predatory nature of it. We talked
about this when we talked about the rules against blood drinking, but it's also
why frankly we fast from meat, right, is permission given later for people to
eat meat. So I'm not saying you have to become a vegan. If you're orthodox, you're
a vegan like half the year, but everyone has to become a full-time vegan, right?
but there is something about meat eating that is not ideal.
Right. The scriptures are very clear about that. And that non-ideal part is that you're
going out and killing. And that represents a fundamentally different relationship to
the rest of creation than what there was in Paradise. Yeah. That's come from there.
And so playing the lyre and pipe, I played the drums in school, so I guess I'm fine.
No, the idea of music is again what it's used for.
Right. Right. Right. Right. Festival, right, which were festivals to pagan gods. They didn't have secular festivals. Right.
And so no, it's not. No. Well, it's like my example. Yeah, because this was about giving people the place in space to indulge there. Yeah.
Yeah. Cause I mean, there's there's often this association of music within a lot of contexts with seduction and all this kind of stuff.
Sad enough.
Right.
Now, that is not saying music is innately evil.
We'll be more in a minute.
Right.
And then you get to a tubal cane and he's making instruments of bronze and iron.
And you say, well, metallurgy, that seems like a nice thing.
This is the idea here is that these are weapons for war, for mass murder.
Right.
Cain to kill somebody with a rock.
But now we've got swords, implements, right.
armor we can go
a war, we can have mass slaughter, we can take what we want, right? And this sort of dovetails
with what gets fleshed out even more like if you look at the version of this genealogy that's
in the Book of Enic and the Book of the Watchers. And we're not going to, I know this is going
to be a let down, but we're not going to talk a lot about giants tonight because we kind
of already did that. Then we do that frequently. We're focusing more on Kane tonight. But obviously,
sleep in nephilum lay at the
end of this, right? The end of this chain. But all along the genealogy, when you read it in the book of the watchers, in the book of Enoch, these demonic spirits are giving the people in Canes line, these secrets, right?
and this knowledge of potions, sorcery, allergy, all of these things, all of these sort of
technique, these technological aspects.
So the idea is that all of them are being given to humanity before humanity is ready to
use them in a way that is good and is righteous.
Right?
So there's not any way to use this technology.
Right.
Yeah.
That's a question.
Whenever we bring this up, we usually get a whole bunch of questions like, well, which technologies
are okay to use and are not from demons?
You know, or how do we know when we're ready or whatever?
And it's like, well, that's not the point.
point is what am I using this for?
What is the purpose, the tealos? What am I accomplishing by using this technology? That's the question.
Right. Yeah. And there's the big example is like nuclear energy, right?
Right. That's a one of good example. We always use we, I mean humans, us humans.
You commanded, right?
Yeah, yeah.
It was a thumb, we make a knife, right?
That's a obscure reference, but.
The any technology we find we immediately use in the most destructive way possible and then maybe later develop
less
weapons based and
Killing based uses for them so
Nuclear technology you can use for power you can use for for all kinds of things medicine. They yeah, yeah
Treat cancer right with radiation right
And the first thing we of course
did with it was massacre
thousands upon thousands of people and I know me saying that now there will be people upset, okay,
but I have to tell you a fact that you may not know
Right, and that should make you more upset about it if you don't know it
before
Harry Truman made the decision to vaporize Nagasaki
It was the most Christian city in Japan. Yeah
Yeah, multiple Christian groups, including...
And I'm not sure it was the largest, but there were at least 14,000 Orthodox Christians
living in Nagasaki before the bomb was dropped.
More than 50% of the Roman Catholics in Japan lived in Nagasaki.
Yeah.
And one day, most of the Christians in Japan, in the most Christian city in Japan, men,
women, children, going about their lives had nothing to do with World War II.
not worshiping the Emperor.
they were Christians were vaporized by a bomb. So you can at me, you can call me
unpatriotic, you could be mad at me about that. Father Andrew might read the
email. But that's the reality. And we have to deal with reality. A bunch of
Christians, your brothers and sisters Christ were murdered. That's it. That's
Yep.
So moving on from that happy note and completely non-controversial with whatever listeners we have left.
The other big way that King gets talked about sort of going forward his legacy in some of these writers has to do with his state as cursed.
Right, so he's sort of taken as the exemplar.
of a human who is sort of fully under this state of curse that we've talked about before.
When we talked about blessings and cursings in 1% and in Deuteronomy 20 through 30, but this
gets sort of developed out as this curse is described.
He sort of take it as exhibit A.
Yeah, and it spreads in the world like as Adam and Eve were supposed to spread blessing
in the world instead what happens is Cursed gets spread. Things get...
messed up by Kane and his descendants.
Yeah, he's the anti-Adam, really.
And a lot of the flood needs to sort of wash this all the way.
But so, a follow-up Alexandria, who I know we've quoted a bunch before,
but just for the record for everybody, is a first century BC Jewish philosopher
in Alexandria, Egypt,
wrote a uh...
A text whose title is roughly questions and answers in Genesis.
It's not just answers in Genesis?
No. Please.
You find it named all kinds of things in translation.
Yeah. Like questions and derogations.
Two questions and...
It's called questions and answers.
Come on, Q&A and Genesis.
Right. Right.
But he has a couple of questions and answers related to Cain
in his curse where he kind of lays in.
this out. Okay, so this is in the first chapter section or book, I'm not sure which, part 71.
The earth is the last portion of the world. Therefore, if that utters curses, we must consider that
the other elements do likewise pour forth adequate maladictions. For instance, the fountains and rivers
and sea in the air and the land and the fire and the light and the sun and moon and stars,
in short the whole
heaven, for if inanimate and earthly nature throwing off the yoke, wars against injury,
why may not still rather those natures do so which are of a pure character. But as for
him against whom the parts of the world carry on war, what hope of safety he can have for
the future, I know not. And the he there, of course, right, is Cain.
Right. Right. And so this is sort of laying out in a more full way, right? This enmity between
and the rest of it.
and the rest of creation.
Yeah. Right.
And if you go and read like various versions of the life of Adam and Eve,
when you read stories of Adam's repentance,
the sun and moon and stars and these same things,
phylogists are all praying with him and offering incense with him
in his repentance.
So there's this idea that in his repentance,
the whole world is cooperating.
Canas in the exact opposite state, his lack of repentance,
hence, his continued evil means that...
he is at odds with everything in the creation.
The whole created order he is now out of whack with
because he won't repent.
Yeah.
And so then he goes on to answer,
I mean, he's posing himself these questions
but he has a rhetorical device.
It's almost like Atticus, I'm really.
Yeah.
And he goes on to talk about a little more about
what all is included in that.
Yeah, okay, so this is part 74.
In the first place, he might have received injury
from the parts of the world, which indeed were made
for the advantage of the good and that they might
partake of them, but which nevertheless
derived from the wicked no slight degree of revenge.
In the second place, it may be that he said this
because he was apprehensive of injury
from beasts and reptiles, for nature has brought forth
these animals with the express object
they're being in.
of vengeance on the wicked. In the third place, some people may imagine that he is speaking with
reference to his parents on whom he had inflicted an unprecedented sorrow and the first evil which
should happen to them before they knew what death was. And of course, the, you know, the thing that
he's referencing Kane saying is like, I'm gonna, I'm gonna die. I'm gonna get killed. Why would
Kane say this? That's essentially the question that he's asking. Right. Right. This is all the stuff
that might have killed him.
Right, right.
Why would he say this?
Yeah.
The first thing is the idea that he's so cut off from the world that the things of the world that
are there to benefit the righteous would actually do him harm. Yeah. Right. And you know, this is
that same idea we see expressed with St. Paul with the Eucharist, right, that someone going and
receiving the Eucharist, like if Cain went and received the Eucharist, it could kill him.
Yeah. Right. Because he is not prepared to receive it. He's not receiving it in repentance.
You just see me get in impurity and wickedness.
And then I love this idea that the animals are at odds with him because that's sort of the vengeance from God, you know, mosquitoes.
Vengeance from the Lord.
But I mean, this is the notion of the left hand of God.
Certain types of animals were brought forth in the world for this purpose.
Right.
For this purpose.
And you're like, wow, that's that makes us out of me.
Right.
Let's get remember what we've said before about
the way God is seen to relate to the demons who he allows in the world.
Yeah.
Throughout the Old Testament and in Second Temple Jewish literature, which is, again,
this is all for bringing about repentance.
Yes, this idea of the left hand of God.
Right.
It's all about trying to bring about repentance, not just a punish, but also this is
this is Philo's answer for the wait.
Did lions eat grass before the explosion for paradise?
for paradise.
right? Like no, all the beasts didn't show up until there were sinners who needed repentance.
And the reptiles. So, wow.
In the, like I said, that's phylozance or I'm not saying that. Yeah, right.
You teach you the church or what the church is saying. That's phylozance or that question.
Yeah. And then the last thing he says, of course, is that he's afraid of his parents. What are they
What are they gonna do to me?
Right.
So this state, the word that's used by Philo and Josephus and other Greek writers to describe
this state of curse that Cain is in is Aeos.
Yeah.
Alpha, gamma, Omicron, sigma, Agos, Agos, yeah.
There's no Ioda.
Yeah.
which is called Holes.
Which is called Holes.
I mean, if I was a himnographer, man, would I make a lot of use of that pun, right?
Which they do.
They do.
There's only one I own a different.
So, yeah, and that word, you know, there's lots of words for cursed, right?
I mean, anathema, right?
You know, that kind of thing.
But in Greek, but this one is about ritual impurity.
Yeah
And it's a particular type of ritual impurity that comes upon a person from sacral age and
murder often when mixed together.
And that sacral age usually takes the form of the desecration of some sacred space.
So both Herodotus and Thucydides use the word to describe people who, for example, massacred
people like Massacre Priests inside some God's temple.
So they defiled the gods temple by murdering people and that means they're now
Ios right there. They're occurred under a curse right there. They have this status of being
Richellian pure
Joe Cephas uses it at a couple of points to describe some massacres that took place in the Jerusalem temple that everyone involved
One time it was just some Levites who took up arms and killed some people not in the temple
but that they had
contracted sort of this state. And the important part of this is that this kind of
cursiveness or the ritual impurity part of this, the ritual impurity part of this, is
not removable.
Yes, this is permanent mark.
You can never be removed. There's no sacrifice for it. There's no ritual washing for it.
There's nothing for it, right? You maintain the ritual impurity. That's not the same as
saying you can't be forgiven for the sin involved.
That doesn't mean there's no repentance, there's no way back.
But the state of impurity, of ritual impurity, cannot be removed.
And there are other places where we see this sort of ritual impurity aspect attached to
Kain, one of which is, in 1 John 3, verse 12.
where when St. John says that came murder.
his brother. The word that's used for murdered there is not the normal word. The word that's used for
murder there is Fadzo, which means literally slaughter. Literally slaughtered his brother.
But in the Greek Old Testament tradition, that word is used entirely for killing a sacrificial
So, St. John uses this word in the
describing Cain and Abel to place what Cain did.
It's not just a Fratricide,
but to place it in this kind of ritual
and ritual impurity context.
Yeah.
And so I know there are people who get worried
anytime you say that like a state of impurity
is not removable and get worried about
or something unforgivable, did they do it?
I'm pretty sure nobody listens.
is gone in massacre, then he priests inside of churches.
So, I mean, this isn't one that you're going to accidentally do.
Just slip one day, have a bad day and do it.
But this idea we see in Scripture, for example, King David is told he can't build the temple
because there's blood on his hands.
Yeah, and it doesn't matter how many sacrifices he offers.
Yeah, and that's not saying like the prophet and King David is not a saint. It's not saying he's not.
Was it holy at the end of his life? It's not saying he was not forgiven for the sins he committed.
All those things are true, but at the same time, right, what he did killing Eriah, right,
I may not be taking Bathsheba, but well actually committing adultery with Bathsheba.
then killing your eye to rid up, then very much.
But right, you can't undo that.
Yeah, like, you know, people can't be.
You can't do it.
Yeah.
But you can't undo it.
Can't fix it.
Able can't be unmertered.
And you know, and this plays out, right?
Like there's cannons in the church,
especially cannons having to do with clergy,
that if they've done various things,
especially if they've killed anyone,
in any way whatsoever, even accidentally,
can't be ordained. And in some cases they have to be removed from the priesthood or the
deaconator of Episcopacy, whatever the order that they're holding. And it's not that
they can't be forgiven, but they can't serve anymore. And I'm reminded of a story, and
I can't remember what the source of this is. So right in, let us know if you happen to
another one. About St. Basel the great who, you know, as you know, he's a bishop.
and he's got priests serving in his diocese.
And one did something and Basil deposed him from the priesthood.
I don't remember what it was at this man did.
He deposed him for the priesthood and sometime later
the two of them are both at the same funeral.
And this ex priest walks up to the body and prays over
and the man comes back to life.
And so then he goes up to Basil and says,
so I mean you see what just happened now.
Can I please be a priest again?
And you know?
And St. Basil says to him,
and now this is the best of my recollection,
you can be a saint, but you can't be a priest again.
You know, what he did left a mark
and that's just the way that it is.
I mean, you can talk about how, you know,
it's wise to do that because it would scandalize people
even if the man was really repentant and so forth,
but there's this deeper thing going on here, you know,
this ritual impurity that just can't
be washed away. Again, you can be forgiven, you can become a saint, which is the goal of Christianity
by the way. The goal of Christianity is not to be redeemed.
Not being a priest, being a saint. Yeah. Yeah. In fact, ordination might even be an impediment to
salvation in many cases. You know, the goal is to be a saint. There's nothing standing in the way
of you becoming a saint. If you willing to repent, you can do it. You know, it doesn't matter what
And that's because sin and curse are not the...
same thing. Right.
Terce is the consequence of sin. Right. And forgiveness does not erase consequences.
The fact that you're forgiven does not mean you don't have to face the consequences.
In fact, when someone comes and asks for forgiveness and says, they're sorry, and you know that
they're only doing it because they're trying to get out of the consequences. Right. That's
considered a bogus apology. Yeah. That's not repentance. Right. Like, I'm really sorry
did it because I got caught, right? Like, that's not how that works, right? So repentance
includes and often begins with accepting the consequences of our actions, whatever they
are. Yeah. Right. And if the consequences of my actions someday, God forbid, mean that
I can't be appreased anymore, then part of my repentance from those actions whenever they
were will be accepting that I can't be one anymore.
Yeah. Yep.
Alrighty. Well, that wraps up the second half of this episode of The Lord of
Spirits. And we've got one more half to go. We're going to take another break, our
final break for this episode, and we'll be right back. Father Andrew Stephen
Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on
the next part of The Lord of Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855 AF Radio.
For all of us, male or female, parent or not, that's what it's often like, isn't it?
It's at the end of our own tether that the miracle happens.
It is in our greatest weakness that God strength is known.
It's when we decrease that He can increase.
It's in losing our life that we find it.
to push it another way.
It's in the...
This spot where Saint Morena falls down, exhausted that her spring rises up.
It's when the people of God curse Moses in the wilderness and wish themselves back in
Egypt, that they hear the crack of the staff, the gush of water through the rock.
It's when God himself is spat upon and mocked and bleeding and dead that the glorious resurrection
is ushered in.
from seven holy women, conversations with saints and friends.
Now available as an author.
audiobook at Audible, Amazon, and iTunes.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Hey, welcome back.
It's the third half of the Lord of Spirits podcast,
and we are in the second part of a three-part series
talking about
the fall of man. First part was about death. This part's about sin. Next time we're going to talk about being dominated by demons.
But today we're talking about sin. We're talking about can as the
sinner. So here we are. It's the third half.
Kind of where do we go from here?
Right? What are we? How do we understand? Well, it's a curse death destruction. The creation hates you, Cain.
Yeah, yeah. Super metal.
Yeah.
I'm trying to think of how many Kane-related metal band names there are.
I mean, there's a Venge 7 fold.
Right.
Anyway.
So, I have not made a special study of this topic.
Would be awesome if there was like an easy listening album or like a yacht rock album.
Something to do with Kane.
Let us know is there a lounge singer out there that you guys love?
I don't know.
Actually, Bluegrass does know about sin.
Yeah, I know.
I can see plenty of Bluegrass song about, uh, about Canaan Able.
Oh, yeah.
Yep.
They might be picking, but they wouldn't be grinning on that one.
Oh, nice.
But, uh, so, uh, where we're going, uh, in this third half, she's shocked.
We're going to end up in first child three versus 12.
Uh, anyways, spoilers.
Oh, spoilers.
What?
Thank you.
Before we go there, by way of a little review, so there's sort of one more thing to talk about with
Cain in terms of 1 John 3 verse 12. And in a lot of ways this aspect of Cain sort of sums up
the rest, right? And so if if
Last, in the last episode, we kind of ended up talking about theosis.
We're now going to talk about the other end of the other genealogy here in terms of
Cain.
But so to start with, we have to quick review, we've talked about this before, but the idea
of fatherhood and how that relates to image bearing, right, in the scriptures, right?
And so being the son of...
something, right?
Means that you are the image of it or the embodiment of it, right? Or the
sort of incarnation of it, right?
So if we look at the common examples, right, Barnabas, right, Barnabas, right?
He is the son of encouragement or the son of
of consolation, right?
And what we're saying there is that he is a person who images or who embodies these qualities.
Yeah. I mean, you know, James and John, right? The sons of thunder, is that...
Same thing.
Yeah, because they're thunder-y guys.
Yeah. Yeah.
Although there's also a riff there, because the place where Jesus calls them that was not far from a shrine to Zusboa Nurgis.
Oh!
the way that's easier. But you know when we'll talk more about that.
one more from today when we talk about Thunder Gods.
Yeah, we're going to do a Thunder Gods episode everybody.
So,
or the Son of Tradition, right?
Right.
And that's literally sort of Son of Destruction.
Yeah, in Greek it's Wios Tis Apollias,
the Son of Destruction.
And then, of course the English word,
Tradition comes.
from a little bit of etymology.
I'm not gonna play the jingle,
but a little bit of etymology.
Tradition comes from Latin,
Peter Dede, which means, you know, to destroy.
Right, it's destruction.
Yes.
And for the record, the road to perdition
is near Holland, Michigan.
Oh, I'm a coast.
That's right.
Anyway.
So,
So all those I
the sun is the image of the Father.
That's the idea that they're embodying
these properties, these qualities, these aspect,
these things, the destruction in a real way.
This is also true with the sons of God language.
That we refer to it with angels and humans.
Especially with humans, sons of God means we're imaging God,
God which we've talked about as we talked about.
last time, right? That sons of God in the same way that image and likeness sort of were
on both ends, right, of the spectrum where I confused everyone. It sort of wraps around
because this is the this is the fiosus as a mobius strip imagery. It's always rough when
to get to that half turn in the middle.
Right.
But, you know, Adam is called the sun.
of God, right? Right. He's he's made of the image of God in St. Luke's genealogy of Christ.
And also we are made sons of God, right? As St. Paul says, right? That like in his aspect,
and that again is the piosus, right? Because we're imaging God in the world, right? So
So uh, Kingdom get called the Son of God.
Uh, that's no.
First job, three verse 12, back again.
We're told that he is of the evil one.
He is the son of the devil.
Remember the first half?
Not mean literally, not literally.
He was conceived aboard the usual way,
but he became the son of the devil.
Right.
He became the son of the devil by what he did.
And this is important to hammer not just because of the kind of wonky theories we started
out talking about, but also because a lot of forms of nosticism, for example, right,
divide humanity into like sons of light and sons of darkness, right, or sons of God
and sons of the devil.
And those are like ontological categories.
You are born as one or the other, right?
like two different
species of human that you're either one or the other.
And has nothing to do with who you are and what you do.
Right?
So, Cain becomes the son of the devil.
He's the first one who sort of becomes the son of the devil.
And he does that, how, by imaging the devil, right?
By bringing the devil's works into the world,
by embodying him, by doing this wickedness,
by committing murder, by doing all these things,
and by teaching them, right?
So not only does he have a demon sort of
of walking him around, but he's then walking other people, right?
He's passing it on to the next generations.
Both a user and a dealer.
Yeah.
Not high on his own supply, though.
Right.
And Christ uses the same kind of language of being the son
of the devil, or the son of the evil one.
Yeah.
So in John chapter 8 verses 39
through 44, you see this conversation between Christ and some of his critics. They answered him.
Critics, that's being polite. I was raised soon to be murderers. Yes, right.
They answered him, Abraham is our father. Jesus said to them, if you were Abraham's children,
you would be doing the works Abraham did. But now you seek to kill me, a man who has told you the
the truth that I heard from God.
This is not what Abraham did.
You are doing the works your father did.
They said to him,
We were not born of sexual immorality.
We have one father, even God.
Jesus said to them,
If God were your father,
You would love me,
For I came from God and I am here.
I came not of my own accord,
But He sent me.
Why do you not understand what I say?
It is because you cannot bear to hear my word.
You are of your father the devil.
and your
will is to do your father's desires.
He was a murderer from the beginning
and does not stand in the truth
because there is no truth in him.
When he lies, he speaks out of his own character
for he is a liar and the father of lies.
Pretty sharp words there from the Lord.
Yeah, kind of uncurrents like.
Wait.
So, right.
Yeah, and so notice.
here, what is it that makes them of their father the devil? Right? It's not
coincidental, St. John's also writing this, and that's why the same kind of
wording appears. The because of what they are doing, right? Crisis of in
in verse 41, you are doing the works your father did, right? Yeah. That's what
makes them, right? And if...
they were sons of Abraham, they would be doing the works.
Abraham did. Right? Right.
So it makes you a son of Abraham.
The son of God is that you do the things God does.
And so again, this is this this active imaging works both ways.
Right? Works both ways.
And so it working in this bad way in this negative
way in this way of sin and wickedness is what we've kind of been calling in a
makeshift word. Then I wish we could open something better but I don't know what.
As demonosis, right? Yeah, I mean demonization maybe but I mean demonosis is
nicely parallel to theoses. Yeah, sort of. It's an actual word. No. It's I mean it is if we all say it is.
Yes.
And I won't go along with your roots anyway.
So the demonic powers are in the world promoting sin,
this force.
And sin, the passions that we talked about last time,
they make people passive and they take over
and they take control.
Nothing they also, that's also transformative.
In the same way that theosis is transformative,
the following Christ is transformative,
that love is transformative, hate is transformative.
In the same way that kindness is transformative,
cruelty is transformative, right?
In an opposite direction.
So these aren't just, I chose to do this,
I could have chosen to do something otherwise.
We assess whether it's morally better good,
We have an ethical.
argument, no, no, no, no, no, no, no. This is much more deeply related to our being and our humanity
and who we are. And it has nothing to do with whether you get caught and has nothing to do with
whether anyone knows it has nothing to do because this is in you, right? If you steal you can
steal your whole life and never get caught and you're still a thief. Yeah. Right. You can kill
and get away with it and you're still a murderer, you still have blood on your hands.
Right? And there's no changing that. There's no changing what has happened to you because of it. Right?
Outside of repentance, right? And and
Transformation in the other direction, but it will change you and I
Know we've used this example before but we probably all know people and have known people who have gone down a dark path in life and
By God's grace turned around at some point and you could physically see when you've looked at them
the difference. So are you saying that when you go down the dark path it doesn't
necessarily forever dominate your destiny? No. Okay. It does not. Um, so and and that
that state of curse, that's what that is. That's what that changes. Right. That's
That's what that negative changes, that's what that is.
That's not there again because...
God's going to punish you for your sins because you've been bad, right?
That's again to drive you to repentance, right?
If we have known those people who have gone down that dark road and have gotten to a point
where just physically they're falling apart mentally, right?
Emotionally, right? Things are crumbling.
A lot of times it's when they hit that wherever that rock bottom is for them.
That's when they turn around. That's what finally kicks in the repentance, right?
Yeah I recall uh
One of one of one of my professors in seminary saying, you know, for a lot of people, the only time they actually will eventually repent is, and this is how he gave it, an event starting with a letter D, death, disease, disaster, divorce, depression.
I mean, you know, I did pass the whole ministry for 13 years and it's often true.
If people are comfortable...
They're not likely to repent.
Just kind of, I mean, it happens, but not super often.
Yeah.
I personally need to be hit over the head with a 2x4.
So to get my attention.
But, right, and this is what we're talking about when we talk about like the Epochalu and
the ancient kings and the kings list, or we talk about the humans in Canes line and
the watchers in the book of Enoch, right?
Or what we saw.
in Genesis chapter 4 tonight, this sort of symbiotic relationship that develops between
humans and these demonic spirits, these demonic powers. It's not symbiotic in a positive
way. It's more parasitic, right? Because there's always promises, right? There's always
promises of power and knowledge and pleasure and this and that, that never quite pay off,
Right? Never quite come to the kind of fruition.
I mean, you think people would read enough fairy tales to know that when a magical being shows up and promises are gonna make you beautiful, rich or powerful,
always say no.
Yeah, but that's when they don't show up anymore.
Right. Right.
Because there's enough fairy tales out there to...
Yeah, it's not a being appears to you. It's a TV commercial or an ad.
Yeah, right. Different modes of enchantment now.
right and it tells you by this go
here do this and then you will be happy, you will be fulfilled, you will, you know,
impress the ladies and or men, you know, whatever, whatever it is that it's promising, right?
And the ultimate result of this for a human like Cain being our exhibit A who gives themselves
over to this is that they become like demons and then even in that same
Bye.
Christmem quote, which we are want to quote, in some cases, like with the Nephilim,
even become demons, become demonic spirits.
So this is, we mentioned last time when we were talking about the expulsion from
paradise that that people have gotten from Milton, this idea that the devil
decided he was going to somehow make God not be God anymore and make
himself be God. Right? Which as we pointed out last time makes
absolutely no sense. Right. Right. Not a thing. Right. But so this is what we've seen with
Cain. Right. The devil was only partly successful with Adam. Cain is where we see the devil's plan
sort of go through to fruition with a human. Right. This is what he wants. This is what his plan
was. This is how he's rebelling against
God is creator and that's if if God's plan is theosis, if that's God's plan for humanity that made
the devil envious, that made him jealous, that made him angry, right, that filled him with his
pride. If that's God's plan, then he is going to make at least some of these humans his images
instead of gods, right, his worshipers instead of gods, his followers instead of gods,
That's where he's
to try and use your God is in the lives and the minds and the hearts and the souls and the bodies
of some of these humans, not because he just loves humans and wants some of his own,
but to destroy them because he knows God loves them and he hates God.
Yeah. Hey, so related to that actually, we just got someone is calling from Kentucky.
At least that's where his phone number is from. I've learned now I can't say that they're in
in Kentucky.
whatever because just that just happens to be where your area code is. But anyways, so
Nathan from Kentucky, are you there? Yes, fathers. Hey, Nathan, welcome to Kentucky. You
are in Kentucky. Great. Well, that's good to know. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
What is your old Kentucky home? Oh, no, I had to move recently. I'm in a new apartment.
Oh, he's his new Kentucky home.
Yes, I'm suddenly hearing
blue moon of Kentucky. I mean, all the, yeah, all the old bluegrass songs and stuff are coming to mind now.
So, so Nathan, what is on your mind about Cane?
So, ever since I listened to you guys and you all talked about the three falls, I noticed that there was like three temptations of Jesus,
And that a lot of them seem to be like
refutations or what you might call
discontinuities with those falls.
So you have the obvious
with the nation and then Satan offering Jesus the nations and him refusing the worship
which you know the humanity gave into. And with of course Adam and Eve in the apples
dealing with God's intent and Jesus with the stone and bread that is also you know him
submitting to our God intended instead of doing his own thing which of course leaves the
Tentation on the temple mount and canes fall and
those two I can't I haven't figured out I can't mesh them and I keep struggling to figure out
what I need to like you know kind of complete this idea.
What do you think Father Stephen is there an alignment between Christ's
facing off with the devil and the wilderness and this this way of talking about three falls of man.
So I'm not totally sold on the idea but yeah if I were to
try to make the link you're wanting to make here. I think this is how I would do it. And
I would have to think about this a lot more before I would endorse even what I'm about to say.
Student from the direction to research and would be great, mother. Yeah. To me, right, because
the issue of throwing himself off of the pinnacle of the temple has to do with trusting in God.
Right? And versus, versus testing God. And I think if I was going to try to connect that with Kane, I would go to after Kane had sinned.
Right? And he hears the curse that he's not going to be able to provide for himself. Right? That the correct thing to do would have been for him to repent and rely on God's protection.
So I don't know what I said. I can't totally sell it, but that's the direction I would maybe go. I think there's a paper in it though Nathan.
So if you have to write any papers anytime soon.
Yeah, if any journal articles or dissertations, you could have that one.
Just warned about against PhD tonight, so I don't know.
Oh, yeah. Well, it's true.
I at least get a mask.
Father, thank you very much. I appreciate that much.
Alright, well thanks very much for calling in Nathan.
All right, well, we're actually getting close to the end here, right?
On our way end my only friend
Yeah, so yeah, yeah, I mean yeah, go ahead. Go ahead
Right, so so yeah, we're talking about the devil sort of his main
plan, right and so
We talked last time about how
Right death gives this our mortality right our death the end of our life in this world and therefore our life
life in this world that's bounded by death gives us this realm for repentance.
And so when we understand that sort of this is what the devil is about, this is what
the devil's plan is, it casts a new light on the idea of sort of morality and repentance.
So a lot of times Christian morality is approached, especially in the modern way.
not just the West in general but the modern West in particular, as Christian morality is trying
to get through life without doing too many bad things. And if you do do those bad things,
as you invariably will do at least some, but when you do do them, you repent of them, meaning
you ask for forgiveness, and then you go on trying not to do it anymore. And that is sort
of a woefully insufficient.
view of morality because morality is spiritual warfare. They're not two separate things.
Yeah. For Cain, he didn't have a moral choice to make about whether it was right or wrong to
murder his brother. Right? Sorry, a manual can't. Right? What if everyone murdered their
brother?
This is untenable, right?
That's not how this works, right? He had to he had this power come upon him
Anger rage resentment. Yeah, that's how it always works, right shame over his own wickedness that caused his sacrifice to be rejected
All of this came over him and he had a choice to yield to it which would result in violence or to fight it
Yeah, and master it
Right. And Christian quote unquote morality is not about maintaining some kind of code
of conduct. It's about self mastery. Yeah. And it's not like ethical choices where you
can sit back and study out. I mean, there are moments like that, right? But generally speaking,
that's not how it goes. And even then, your reasoning is going to be affected by the kind
a person that you are, you know, you can talk yourself into any
anything. Right. You can, well, yes, and right, in order to get to the point where you
could placidly sit and say, I am facing this situation, what is the right thing to do? You
have to have achieved self mastery. Yeah. Because otherwise you're not going to be able
to sit down and make that choice. You're going to do, you're going to react. You're going
to act based on whatever's in the driver's seat, whether it's anger, whether it's lost,
whether it's your laziness, whether it's...
resentments, whether it's you know, irritation, stress, whatever it is, right? And this is across the board, right?
Self-control, right?
James talks about taming your tongue. If we can master ourselves, if we can master the forces that are acting upon us,
right?
That is what then allows us to follow Christ and to serve God and to do good.
but that's the basis of
of the ethical or the moral struggle for a Christian.
It's resisting the desires, the passions,
the forces acting upon us, trying to drive us,
be tossed to and fro, like St. Paul says.
And being able to do and to act and to follow Christ.
Yeah, and, you know, an important important...
The important point to make here is that we, as human beings, do not know who is actually
engaging in the struggle, right?
Someone might look super sinful to us, but actually be really struggling hard.
Someone might look pious and righteous to us, but actually just be yielding to all of,
you know, every temptation that comes.
We're almost always 180 degrees wrong.
Yeah.
Right.
Seriously.
are the
good and upright know what people are almost always scumbags. The people we think are scumbags are
almost always holy people. Yeah. So I've got all those holy fools. Yeah. Yeah. That's why I'm so
popular. I'm a scumbag. There you go. I'll sell some books. Yeah. We'll put that on my tombstone.
There you go. I must come back. That's not so popular. Right?
All right, so in wrapping up and summarizing a lot of what we've talked about and applying,
the thought that came to me especially was, as I've mentioned a number of times on this, so I'm
the father of four kids. And the other day I actually brought all four of those kids to a candy store,
which is not something that we do regularly, but there was a new candy store and so we're like,
Okay, well, we'll give them their
other a few minutes by herself, take the kids to a candy store. And you know, naturally
of course, especially the younger kids are the more they're ready to just grab hold of
in the candy store. And you know, a father's job is to say, here's the limit, everybody.
I brought you the candy store, I'm not telling you you can't have any candy. But here's
the limit. You can have this many or this much, right? And then when we get home, you cannot
it. You may have this much and then save some for tomorrow, right? And this is a normal part of
parenting, right? Father's and mother's both do this. And the thing that occurs to me, especially in
light of, especially we were just talking about about the the Christian struggle and morality and so
forth, mastering the demonic influence that's attempting to leap upon us.
to take hold of us, is that the way that we do that is through these small choices, right?
With raising children, a lot of what you're trying to teach your children to do
is to restrain themselves, to have self-restraint. Like, yes, I understand you have a desire for candy
and maybe I did a foolish thing by putting this all in front of you, but also, you know, we're
We're trying to enter into this and to have some
restraint. You can have one piece, you can have two pieces, you can have three pieces,
whatever it might be. But the same is true for us adults, except theoretically, by the time
we're out on our own, we're training ourselves. We now have been given the tools by our parents
and we're continuing to get counsel from our spiritual fathers and our spiritual brothers
and sisters encouragement to restrain ourselves, to master ourselves, to master...
that desire that comes up within us, right?
Now, candy is a desire that seems kind of small
and unimportant, sure.
But if you feed yourself as much candy as you want,
and you give it to yourself every single day,
then you are not just teaching yourself that that's okay,
you are forming yourself into someone
for whom this is the norm.
You're forming yourself into something.
someone who simply has a desire and then fulfills it. I see something I want it. I'm going
to take it. Right? And while we don't imagine ourselves to be doing horrifying things like,
you know, murder and rape and theft and, you know, whatever else, right? The road there,
road to perdition is gotten there. We get there by many small steps of training our...
ourselves to be that way. Right? Almost no one wakes up one day and just suddenly snaps
into being someone who just grabs whatever they desire. They have been transformed in
that direction. They've been transformed in that direction. Right? That yes, it's true
that the slippery slope argument is a logical fallacy, but it is a spiritual reality. You
you know, it is a spirit.
reality. You gradually had deeper and deeper into sin. And holiness works in the opposite way.
You train yourself to have that self-restraint. You train yourself to have self-sacrifice, to have
humility. You engage in the little prayers that is simply daily prayers morning and evening
prayer. Right, if you engage in the little bit of fasting, let's ask
for a couple times a week and then in longer periods
at other times.
If you engage in these things, what you do then
is you gradually build your ability, frankly,
to become like God.
You do the works that he does, and we train ourselves
in small ways initially, and then it becomes greater and greater.
The Lord said this, right?
You've been faithful over little and now receive much.
right? And so if you say to yourself, you know, I don't need to be
obedient in this little thing, then what you're training yourself is to be
disobedient in great things. That's how it always goes. That's how it
always always goes. And so I think one of the big lessons from the story of
King comes again from that that crouching sin that's at his door.
God says, look, it's going to master you.
You've got to master.
this is God behaving as a spiritual father to Cane.
You know, encouraging him.
Like you're going down the wrong paths or you need to come back.
And this is what spiritual fathers and mothers
and spiritual brothers and sisters do for those that God has brought to them.
It's to say, come back.
And so when someone says to you, hey, chill out, restrain yourself.
You know or hey take a look. Just look at where you're going
You got it. Don't be like Kane. Don't be like Kane. You got to turn back and come back to the Lord and
do his works. And so we become truly then the sons of God. Father Steven
So you know there's certain
Issues with this audio only format because with the title of the episode I've been dangling from wires this whole episode in
I just realized I heard some wishing in the background and kind of I heard some
wishing and kind of wonder what that was.
Anyway, so this week is as I was kind of thinking about
Kane and how he ended up living his life after what he did in the choices he
made. I heard some comments from...
Christopher Lash who was talking about our sort of contemporary culture of overwhelming narcissism
and he pointed out that the way we look at our lives now has a lot of affinities with how
Josephus described came living his. Right? And you know it's obvious we can all think about some
celebrities with rap.
or something. We think of people who are just sort of totally debauched and
wicked or violent or you know some kind of arch criminal or these kind of
things as being that type of person. But there's a much more nuanced version
that is ultimately a version of the same thing that is how a lot of us live
our lives.
that we're not looking for gratification of sort of crass
sensual desires all the time, we may not be promiscuous or
substance addicted or those kind of things. But we're looking
to satiate certain desires of our ego and of our pride
and our desire for even even a lot of
This will be controversial but oh well.
Even a lot of the search for meaning stuff now
has an undercurrent of this in it.
That each of us sort of looks at our individual lives,
we say, hey, I have this one life to live.
That's what I've got and I need to make the most of it.
And again, most of us aren't,
crash about it but we make the most of it
because we wanna be successful at something.
We wanna make a name for ourselves.
You want to be recognized by others.
We want to get our ego stroked.
We want sort of money as a measure of that sort of success and that we're doing well and
we're doing the right things and we're the right kind of person.
And we're willing to spend a lot of that money to make ourselves appear publicly whether
we're talking about clothes or whether we're talking about carefully curating our online
profiles to give the right impression to everyone of who we are and that we believe
and thank you.
the right things and we're on board with all the right causes and we support the current
thing. And all of this, we devote all of our time to this. And then at some point along
the line we kind of look and go, hey, I've spent my whole life chasing Maman, what's the
meaning of all this? None of this really means anything. And it never did. And then we go
So, I look for...
meaning. But what Christopher Lash pointed out is that that way of living life is very recent.
That's not how most people in the history of the world or even most people in the world today
live their lives. Most people in the history of the world and the world today live their lives,
he said, like a thread stretched between their parents and their children.
That their life is not this individual thing that belongs to them, for them to maximize and
curated and vass.
in such a way that it has an ultimately gratifying shape and result. Their life is a connection
between the generation before and the generation after, between the past and the future.
And if we approach life less like Cain, and we want to be less like Cain, a good place to start is
Going to the generation above
us, trying to learn from them and what they have to teach us. And that's a whole lot of things.
Every day people pass away with stories and truths and knowledge and experiences
that vanish because none of us cared enough to talk to them and learn them and be able to pass
them on.
And every day people younger than us struggle to figure out what to do and how to live and where
they belong in their communities and in the world, because we don't go to them and pass these
things along to them and help guide them into where they need to be.
Because what our life is really about is about being a part of something much bigger than
ourselves.
So
that St. Augustine was getting at in the city of God.
What our life is about is contributing our little bit
to the history of God's salvation of His creation,
contributing our little bit to the story of the progress
of Christ's gospel.
And we do that through these little small things
that we could all do every day,
to play our part and our shift and our time.
on this earth by being a part of our communities, our families, our church. And when we get plugged in
and we're playing that part, the meaning thing, the idea of what our role is, the idea of what we should be
doing, those things all immediately start to clarify. They immediately start to clarify when we stop
approaching the world in the universe.
and life and Christ as individuals disconnected and alienated from everything else.
And we start approaching everything together.
Those are my thoughts.
Amen.
Well, that is our show for today.
Thank you, everyone, for listening.
If you didn't get through to us live this time, we'd still like to hear from you.
You can email us at LordofSpirit.angianfaith.com.
You can message us at our Facebook page.
or you can leave us a voicemail. Let's...
www.nakepipe.com slash Lord of Spirits.
And join us for our live broadcasts on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7pm
Eastern 4pm Pacific.
And if you are on Facebook, you can like our page, join our discussion group, leave reviews
and ratings everywhere.
But please, most importantly, share this show with a friend whom you know is going to love
it.
It's all about the word of mouth.
And finally, be sure to go to www.hfates.com, stroke support, and help make sure we and lots
other AFR podcasters stay on the air and have yourself some only good caves.
The chicken fingers which are better than Chick-filth.
Thank you, good night, and God bless you.
Stay mad, everybody.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priest.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung,
a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels
round about the throne and the beasts and the elders.
And the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000
than thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice,
worthy is the land that was slain to receive power
and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12